guys welcome to Concept in coding this
is Shan and today in spring board we are
going to start at The transactional
annotation but before that I would
highly recommend you to watch this two
videos the one is the concurrency
control which I have shared in the hld
playlist and another is the spring boot
aop which we have just recently covered
in the spring boot playlist okay so if
you already know about this two concept
then we are good to go and let's start
it so one thing before we start we have
to understand about critical section so
it's a very simple critical section
definition so it's a code segment where
shared resources are being accessed and
modified okay so now let's say that this
is my shared resource you so a cab okay
so in DB let's say that this car has ID
10001 and currently status is available
now now there is a code segment where we
are accessing this sh shared resource
and also trying to
update okay so this why it's known
as critical section so now what happen
is when multiple requests try to access
this critical section data inconsist
inconsistency can happen now let's say
that four people are trying to book a
cap parallel so now let's say say that
four requests comes here in the critical
section in parallel so all will read car
with one1 yes they will all read
successfully if status is available yes
current status is available update it to
book for all four they will like your
car is booked your car is booked your
car is booked your car is booked if
critical section is not handled properly
right then during multiple requests data
inconsistency can
happen so what is the solu solution the
solution is usage of
transaction the transaction helps to
achieve asset property we like during
first year I think or second year we all
have studied assd property in the DB
right so we just to remind you that the
first a in the asset is
atomicity atomicity says that in a
transaction if any operation fails the
entire transaction will get roll back
what does it mean quickly let's say that
in a DB a has 10 Rupees B has 20 rupees
now this is your transaction in
transaction let's say you want to debit
a 5 rupees you want to credit B 5 rupees
this is a particular let's say
transaction one okay so now what
atomicity says that
first these are operation Operation one
operation two okay so let's say that
first operation executed you debited a
so now it would be like 5 rupees now
during credit some failure happened and
this operation got failed the credit
operation got failed so as per the
automac city if any operation fail the
entire transaction will get roll back so
entire transaction whatever the
operations are there previous operation
will get
roll back so means this debit operation
which got success will also get roll
back so this instead of 5 rupees it will
again goes back to 10 Rupees okay so
that's what
actually lead to consistency which says
that before and after the transaction
our DB should be consistent only so my
DB was in consistent State 10 rupees and
20 rupees right A and B
after running the
transaction right whether it's a
successful or failure doesn't matter
right if it is a success my DB state
would be a would be let's say 5 rupees
and B would be 25 rupees so this state
of a DB is also consistent if there is a
failure so again my DB state would be
consistent okay so this property
consistency says that no matter after
and before for the transaction my DB
should be consistent only there should
not be any inconsistency like okay the
debit got successfully happen 5 rupees
but credit doesn't happen so credit is
still 20 rupees that is inconsistent
State okay so both are linked to each
other then there is something called
isolation isolation says that even if
multiple transactions are running in
parallel they do not interfere with each
other so this is just one operation
right you need to debit a 5 rupes credit
B 5 rupees this is just a one
transaction there could be let's say
multiple transaction running in parallel
there could be another transaction like
debit a 2 rupees credit b 2 rupees there
could be another
transaction credit a debit B something
something X Y something so what I'm
trying to say is that multip transaction
can run at the same time but they will
feel like they are running individually
independently right in an isolation
environment like nobody's interfering to
each other okay so now let's say that
everybody wants to update a transaction
one transaction 2 transaction 3 and if
there are any more all wants to update a
so trans ction makes sure that one only
one of them will take a lock on this and
one of them only will update it okay and
once the lock is free then only it will
be given to another transaction and then
it will work so internally transaction
make us proper
sequence even though from the outside
world we all see that all transactions
are running in parallel but it's not
right internally transaction make use of
locking and make sure that the
operations
are in proper sequence manner so each
transaction feels that they are running
in an isolation and no no multiple
transaction interfere with each
other and the last one is durability
which says that once your transaction
let's say this transaction done its
operation and it done
commit now once the commit is happened
right this data is persisted means now
even if your system cash this data
should not get lost okay so that's what
durability says that and all this
atomicity consistency isolation and
durability guarantee is provided by
transaction and that's why it is very
very popular into during Financial kind
of applications all financial
application mostly use uh which DB which
have which provide this asset
property okay so generally this is like
you begin a
transaction then you have your
operations then if all operations got
success you do commit means you
persisted into the DB else if any
failure your roll back will happen right
roll back of all
transactions and you end the
transaction so you have to do this you
have to do
this and now understand that in your
application let's say you have 100
methods you have 100 methods or I would
say that thousand methods so let's say
that you have th000 methods which where
it is
actually touching the
DB okay so let's say that this is
update update uh
user so it is actually touching the DB
right update bulk user this is also
actually updating the DB update user bu
ID something this is by email ID
something different different flavors
right so all these are actually
internally touching the
DB so you have to use this transaction
for
each now here if you see that your
actual business logic is this only which
one is your actual business logic
actually
this debit from a credit to B but here
if you see that the lot of things you
have to do just for the
transactional just to achieve the asset
property begin if all success commit
else roll back and transaction but if
you focus this red only this is actual
your business logic rest is all the
verbos right this is and if you see that
there's lot of duplicate you have to do
you have to do in this method this
method this method this is just one
class if there are hundreds of class
multiple methods in all methods you have
to put begin transaction end transaction
if all success commit else roll back and
then you have to put your
operation so this can be simplified
through at theate transactional
annotation in a spring
boot right so in a spring boot we can
achieve this through this
annotation so if you want to use this
annotation you have to add certain
dependency
so this two dependency you have to add
the first dependency is like depending
upon your which DB you are using so
let's say if you using relational DB
then data jpa works fine right from this
data jpa you can you can get at the rate
transactional
annotation right if you are not using
relational DB you are using no SQL
because there are many uh no SQL DB
which also provide transactional support
so this dependency will get changed
depend upon the DB which you are using
okay because you need at the rate
transaction annotations but it is coming
from which dependency depend upon the
DB and now since DB got involved you
have to use a particular driver also
database driver
also so this is the second dependency
you have to add so in the pal you also
have to add database
driver right and in application.
property you have to provided username
and password also so this database
driver I haven't uh explaining you here
what is the dependency and what things
you have to put in application. property
because in the next topic after at
theate transaction we will cover this in
depth for now like whatever the DB you
are using for learning right uh you can
just check what is the database driver
dependency in a spring board
documentation you will get that add this
into the pom.xml right so that will
works
out but this two dependency you have to
add and also this is
optional right at theate enable
transaction Management in your spring
boot application class main where you
are actually the main method is there
this is optional because even if you
don't write I told you that a spring
boot automatically configures so many
things for us so it will add it for us
even if you don't write it but just for
uh mentioning that this is also required
let's say that somehow spring do not add
it let's say what would happen then in
whatever method you have put at theate
transactional annotation right that will
not be read so it's like we have to
enable the transaction management
actually right so with that once this
available spring boot scan for and look
for at theate trans external
specifically but generally it's not
added it's automatically added by
springboard just a heads
up okay now at theate transactional
property can be applied at class level
and at method level if you applied at
the class level then it will
automatically get applied to all the
public
methods but not at the private
method okay
and if you are using at the method level
it will get applied to only particular
method only so now you are using
transaction so only update car now all
this is now your critical section kind
of so all this code inside this is now
your critical section right and it would
get handled through like begin
transaction right all your business
logic right and if any failure inside
this operation roll back will happen and
after all successful commit will happen
right this will but not for this because
this is Method
level okay so now transaction Management
in Spring boot uses aop that's why I
told you that aop is the first
prerequisite which you should know
because here you have to know about
point cut and advice which we have
explained in aop otherwise you will not
understand how transaction management
actually works internally
so what happen is internally transaction
management this annotation right at
theate
transactional uses aop I told you the
use of aop that aop tolds that hey you
focus on your business logic right and
all the verbos like duplicate code I can
take care of it and now I already told
you that here this is all duplicate you
have to write in each and every method
which you which is like duplicate right
and only this is your business logic you
have to concentrate only this debit from
a and credit to B this all verbos is not
actually your program so that's where
aop comes into the picture
so all this now we are using at the rate
transaction only but where is actually
begin
transaction all success then do commit
else any failure do roll back and
transaction where all this trans where
where are all this
code it is present inside a particular
aspect okay I will tell you how how it
done where it is present but this verbos
code is present there and it has a
placeholder join point you already know
that from the previous right in the
joint point it invokes your method
okay so this is actually your business
logic so you focus on this method right
adding all this things aop will take
care of it just by this
annotation okay so internally aop uh
internally atate transactional what I
told you right it uses aop aop has Al
aop has point cut
expression point cut expression and
advice and advice okay so the point cut
expression which it might be using is
like this at theate within and the path
of this annotation
transactional so all the package
subpackage right it will look for all
the classes and inside all the classes
all the method which has this
annotation if any method it found that
it has at theate transactional
annotation the match will happen the
point cut expression match will happen
and when the point cut expression match
will happen you know that what generally
happen is advises
run okay the advice is run and what is
the advice here now once the point cut
expression matches in at the rate
transactional it runs an around type
advice so there are three type of advice
I told you
after before and
around so the this around type is
generally used for at theate
transactional right and where is this
advice method which is
executed it is present inside the
transactional Interceptor
class and this is the your method which
is act as an
advice okay so now here if you see I
showing you the code I have written a
very very simple controller class okay
this controller class I have given a
name user controller right and the API
is slash API
slash update user okay so/ API and I
have created a method called update user
and this is the get uh get mapping
generally it should be post mapping
because I'm trying to update okay this
is just an example you can change it so
this is the API I wanted to expose slash
update user okay inside this I am
calling this dependency I have put an
autowire on user so this so user. update
user now here if you see that in the
update user method I have used at theate
transactional
annotation okay so now at theate
transactional proper uh annotation
brings me all the capability of
assd right so now what how this actually
works where is begin and all these
things so you know that first point when
you start an
application the point cut
expression will match the point cut
expression let's say that this is the
point cut
expression okay so using this point cut
expression it is able to see that yes
this is a
match a method has this annotation
that's what we are looking for now what
advice has to run okay so which is the
advice so inside a transactional
Interceptor class there is this method
invoke within
transaction this isn't nothing but an
advice right so this will get
invo so now here if you see that in this
advice
method you will see that first it will
create a
transaction okay then it will invoke
your
method right so your transaction is
started like this begin
transaction transaction is started then
you can perform your operation this is
the place it invokes your method so this
method will get invoked now you perform
your update
query now if any exception comes if any
exception come what it will do is it
will catch it and it will inside this it
will roll back
if you go inside this complete
transaction after throwing you will see
that it would it would be doing roll
back but if there is no exception
everything is Success it should do
commit so all success it is doing commit
transaction now no matter if you
have if you have hundreds of classes
like this user there is another table
let's say employee there is another uh
table let's say like order another class
you have so many classes and each class
has multiple methods 10 10 methods which
is quiring the DB updating the DB right
modifying the DB so you have you don't
have to write all this in each and every
method you will just use at theate
transactional now here if you see that
this code is used only at once right you
don't have to duplicate it and this is
not even part of your code this is
coming from a spring boot framework
itself so this is not so you are just
just concentrating on your method your
just method got invoked here you are
just concentrating on your business
logic okay so let's let me tell you this
like so the same thing I have this
controller
class okay one simple update method you
can change it to post mapping uh okay
update User it's calling an update user
method and inside this update user
method this is again at theate component
uh managed by Spring boot but I have put
at theate transaction here so currently
I'm not throwing any exception here
let's say everything got success now
let's say that I am starting my
application okay so I have started my
application okay now let's run this so I
am hitting this API update user / API SL
update
user so now when I hit this now here if
you see the first control goes to
into this method invoke within
transaction is there in transaction
aspect support if you see that the
transaction Interceptor class right it
extends from transaction aspect support
itself so it's a parent class of the
transaction Interceptor generally so
this transaction aspect support is
nothing but a parent class of
transaction Interceptor so here invoke
within transaction get invoked now
currently it what it is doing is it it
is creating a
transaction after that it will proceed
our it will call our method now here if
you see our method call so what now you
can run your operations whatever the
operation you have to run update DB
whatever now what would happen is once
the operations are performed if
everything is Success it will try to
commit so commit
successful now let's say that instead of
all success I am throwing an exception
new run exception I'm throwing some
runtime exception now let's start an
application
again okay so now I'm hitting the API
again so first it will create a
transaction once the transaction is
begin transaction happen it will try to
invoke our method now our method is
throwing an exception so it has been
catch and if you go inside this what it
is doing is it is doing roll back
okay so actually it does roll
back so you got it how internally just
by putting at theate
transactional everything magically works
out so there is nothing magic everything
code is there but only thing is it is
hidden from us spring boot is taking
care of
it right but internally we are still
doing the same
thing so now you know how the
transaction works now we have to
understand all these things much better
way what is transaction
context different types of transaction
manager programmatic and
declarative the
propagation right very important so
there are different type of propagation
isolation
level configure transaction timeout what
is readon transaction and many more
so we will go in this depth in next part
of this video I'll see you in the next
part of this video and there we will
cover all the remaining part of the
transition
annotation thank you bye